<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-minei-pce-association-group-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCE association group">
    PCEP Extensions for establishing relationships between sets of LSPs</title>

    <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I." surname="Minei">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
	  <city>Mountain View</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>94043</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>inaminei@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Edward Crabbe" initials="E." surname="Crabbe">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>edc@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	
    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>170 West Tasman Dr.</street>
	  <city>San Jose</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>95134</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hariharan Ananthakrishnan" initials="H." surname="Ananthakrishnan">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
	  <city>Sunnyvale</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>94089</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>hanantha@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Xian Zhang" initials="X." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>F3-5-B R&amp;D Center, Huawei Base Bantian, Longgang District
</street>
	  <city>Shenzhen</city>
	  <region>Guangdong</region>
	  <code>518129</code>
	  <country>P.R.China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>zhang.xian@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


	<author fullname="Yosuke Tanaka" initials="Y." surname="Tanaka">
      <organization>NTT Communications Corporation</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>Granpark Tower 3-4-1 Shibaura, Minato-ku
</street>
	  <city>Tokyo</city>
	  <region></region>
	  <code>108-8118</code>
	  <country>Japan</country>
	</postal>
	<email>yosuke.tanaka@ntt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="27" month="June" year="2014" />

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
    <t> This document introduces a generic mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs in the 
       context of stateful PCE. 
       This grouping can then be used to define associations between sets of LSPs or between a 
       set of LSPs and a set of attributes (such as configuration parameters or behaviors), 
       and is equally applicable to the active and passive modes of stateful PCE.
       </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the Path Computation Element
      Protocol PCEP.  PCEP enables the communication between a Path Computation
      Client (PCC) and a Path Control Element (PCE), or between PCE and PCE,
      for the purpose of computation of Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) for Traffic
      Engineering Label Switched Path (TE LSP) characteristics.
      </t>

      <t><xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce'>Stateful pce</xref>  specifies a 
      set of extensions to PCEP to enable stateful
      control of TE LSPs between and across PCEP sessions in compliance with
      <xref target="RFC4657"/> and focuses on a model where LSPs are configured 
      on the PCC and control over them is delegated to the PCE. The model of 
      operation where LSPs are initiated from the PCE is described in 
      <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-pce-initiated-lsp'></xref>.
      </t>
	  
       <t> This document introduces a generic mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs. 
       This grouping can then be used to define associations between sets of LSPs or between a 
       set of LSPs and a set of attributes (such as configuration parameters or behaviors), 
       and is equally applicable to the active and passive modes of stateful PCE.
       </t>


    </section> <!-- Introduction -->

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the following terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>: PCC, PCE, PCEP Peer.
	  </t>

    </section> <!-- Terminology -->
 

    <section anchor="Overview" title="Architectural Overview">
     <section anchor="Motivation" title="Motivation">
	 <t> 
         Stateful PCE provides the ability to update existing LSPs and to instantiate new ones. 
         To enable support for PCE-controlled make-before-break and for protection, there is a need
         to define associations between LSPs. For example, the association between the original 
         and the reoptimized path in the make-before break scenario, or between the 
         working and protection path in end-to-end protection. Another use for LSP grouping is for
         applying a common set of configuration parameters or behaviors to a set of LSPs. 
         Rather than creating separate mechanisms for each use case, this draft defines a generic one. 
	 </t>
      </section><!-- Motivation -->
	 
      <section anchor="Operation-overview" title="Operation overview">
	 <t>
	 LSPs are associated with other LSPs with which they interact by adding them
	 to a common association group. Association groups as defined in this document are locally 
         meaningful at the LSP head-end, and can only be applied to LSPs originating at that head end. Thus, the 
         association identifiers are unique at each head end, but not necessarily across the network, and are
         owned and managed by the head end. </t>
      <t> 
         Multiple types of groups can exist, each with their own identifiers space. The definition of the
         different association types and their behaviors is outside the scope of this document.
         The establishment and removal of the association relationship can be done on a per LSP basis. 
	  There is support for removal of all LSPs from an association as well. 
	 An LSP may join multiple association groups, of different or of the same type. 
        </t> 
      </section><!-- Operation overview -->
     </section><!-- Overview -->
     

		
    <section anchor="association" title="LSP association groups">
	
	<t> 
        Association groups are owned by the PCC, but the PCE may request creation of
        an association group (for example before instantiating LSPs that belong to that group).
        Membership in an association group can be initiated by either the PCE or the PCC. 
        Association groups and their memberships are defined using the Association object.
        </t> 

	<t> The Association Object is an optional object in the PCupd, PCRpt and PCinit messages. </t> 
	
		
        <t>The format of the Association object is shown <xref target="Association-Object-Fmt"/>:</t>

        <figure anchor="Association-Object-Fmt" title="The Association Object format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

0               	1               	2               	3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |Type   |  Generic flags    |R| Type-specific flags             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |             Association group id                              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   //            Optional TLVs	                                  //
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

	      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
	
       <t> 
       Type - the association type (for example protection or make-before-break). The association type
       will be defined in separate documents.
       </t>

       <t> 
       Generic flags - flags for the association object. A single one is defined, the R flag indicating 
       removal from the association group.
       </t>
	
       <t> Type-specific flags - specific to the association type, will be defined at the time of the association type.
       </t> 

       <t> Association group id - identifier of the association group. The values 0 and 0xffffffff are reserved. Value 0 is used
       when the PCE requests allocation of an association group. Value 0xffffffff indicates all association groups. </t> 
	
	</section> <!-- lsp association -->

	<section  anchor="association-use" title="Using the LSP association group">

	 <t> 
	  Membership in an association group is reported in PCRpt messages by including the association object along with the LSP
	  object. Removal of the LSP from 
	  the association group on the PCC (for example through configuration) is reported by including the association object 
	  with the R flag set. When an LSP belongs to multiple association groups, multiple association objects are included in 
          the PCRpt, one for each association the LSP belongs to.  
	  A PCE can associate an LSP that was delegated to it (the candidate LSP) 
	  with an existing association group, by sending a PCUpd for the candidate LSP, including the Association Object 
	  for the association group. Error 
	  handling for this operation will be defined in a future version of this draft. 
	 </t> 

	 <t> 
	  An association group can be created locally at the PCC (for example through configuration) or it can be requested by the 
	  PCE. A PCE may request the creation of an association group by sending a PCUpd message with the reserved value 0. In 
	  response to this request, the PCC will allocate an association group id and report it in the PCRpt message. Error handling
	  will be defined in a future version of this draft. Note that this operation includes creation of the group and association
	  of one LSP with this group. Requesting the creation of an association group before the LSP exists will be handled in a 
	  future version of this draft. 
	 </t> 
        </section> <!-- association-use -->
	
	

   
	<section anchor="IANA-considerations" title="IANA considerations">
	  
  
        <t>This document defines the following new PCEP Object-classes and
        Object-values:</t>
        <texttable anchor="Object-Code-Points" style="none" suppress-title="true">
          <ttcol align="center">Object-Class Value &nbsp;</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left" width='50%'>Name </ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference </ttcol>
          <c></c><c>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</c><c></c>
          <c>TBD</c><c>Association</c><c>This document</c>
          <c></c><c>Object-Type</c><c></c>
          <c></c><c>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;1</c><c></c>
        </texttable>
   

     
        <t>This document requests that a registry is created to manage the Flags
        field of the Association object. New values are to be assigned by Standards
        Action <xref target="RFC5226"/>. 
        </t>

	   
	</section> <!-- IANA -->
	
   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     
     <t> The security considerations described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce'></xref> 
   apply to the extensions described in this document.  Additional
   considerations related to a malicious PCE are introduced, as the PCE may now create additional state
   on the PCC through the creation of association groups. 

  </t> 
   </section>

   <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
     <t>We would like to thank Yuji Kamite and Joshua George  for
     their contributions to this document.</t>
    </section>
	
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>
    	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pce-initiated-lsp"?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
    	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.tanaka-pce-stateful-pce-mbb"?>
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"?>
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4657.xml"?>
   </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
