<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-minei-pce-traffic-mapping" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Traffic mapping">
    Enabling Stateful PCE to Tag Label Switched Paths</title>

     <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I." surname="Minei">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ina@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
	<author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2000 Innovation Drive</street>
          <city>Kanata</city>
          <region>Ontario</region>
          <code>K2K 3E8</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    
    <author fullname="Edward Crabbe" initials="E." surname="Crabbe">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>edc@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
	 <author fullname="Julien Meuric" initials="J." surname="Meuric">
      <organization>FT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email></email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="October" year="2013" />

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t> 
	    An active stateful PCE can change characteristics of label switched paths (LSPs), 
		or even initiate the creation of LSPs. How these LSPs are used for forwarding traffic 
		has been considered a topic outside of PCEP's scope. Regardless of how such a mapping
		is implemented, it requires the ability to identfiy the LSP or LSPs to use for forwarding in 
        a flexible way.		
        This document proposes an extension to PCEP to allow tagging LSPs for the purpose
		of traffic mapping.		
      </t> 
    </abstract> 

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce"/> specifies the PCEP extensions
      in support of active stateful PCEs. A PCC can delegate its LSPs to the PCE, 
	  allowing the PCE to update various attributes (such as path or bandwidth) <xref
      target="I-D.crabbe-pce-pce-initiated-lsp"/> specifies a mechanism allowing
      a PCE to dynamically instantiate LSPs on a PCC by sending the path and
      characteristics of the LSP. In both cases, the PCE takes an active role, 
	  initiating changes in the network without the PCC initiating this interaction. 
	  This model makes an active stateful PCE a very attractive building block for SDN
	  solutions.</t>
	  
	  <t>When integrating a stateful PCE in a larger solution, the mapping of traffic
	  to the LSPs is an important function. Two decisions must be taken to allow for such a 
	  mapping: 1) which traffic should be mapped (forwarding equivalence class 
	  identification), for example "map all traffic with destination port xxx" 
	  and 2) which is the LSP onto which the traffic should be forwarded (LSP identification), for 
	  example "LSP to destination yyy, with latency guarantee x".
	  Note that: 
	  a) multiple forwarding equivalence classes (FECs) may be mapped to the same LSP, b) one FEC 
	  may be mapped to one or more LSPs and c) the mapping should be communicated in a way that allows
	  both PCE-controlled and non-PCE-controlled LSPs to be used, and allows both a central and 
	  a distributed mode of operation, so as to allow deployment of 
	  this function in a mixed network. </t>

      <t>Similar to how a route may be associated with one or more communities in BGP, an LSP 
	  may be tagged with one or more opaque LSP-tags to allow for easy LSP identification. This 
	  association may be 1) configured on the router or 2) communicated by an active stateful PCE or
	  3) distributed in a dynamic way (outside the scope of this document). This draft defines the 
	  procedures for associating an LSP-tag to an LSP in PCEP.</t> 
      
    </section> <!-- Introduction -->

    <section title="Terminology">

      <t>The following terminologies are used in this document:

      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="LSR:"> Label Switching Router.</t>
        <t hangText="PCC:"> Path Computation Client.</t>
        <t hangText="PCE:"> Path Computation Element</t>
        <t hangText="PCEP:"> Path Computation Element Protocol.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

    </section> <!-- Terminology --> 

    <section anchor="LSP-TAG-TLV" title="LSP TAG TLV">

      <t>The LSP TAG represents an opaque valure to be associated with an LSP. The 
      same LSP TAG may be associated with several LSPs by sending the LSP-TAG in a 
	  PCUpd message for each of them. One LSP may be associated
      with multiple LSP TAGs by specifying them in separate TLVs. 
	  The operator may define the opaque tag in any way that 
	  is convenient operationally, for example he may choose to embed the LSP 
	  destination address in the LSP TAG. The tags associated with an LSP may change
	  during the lifetime of the LSP (for example, if a tag represents compliance to a
	  latency bound, when the LSP is rerouted along a non-compliant path, the tag would need to 
	  be removed to avoid mapping delay-sensitive traffic to it).</t>

      <figure anchor="LSP-TAG-TLV-FORMAT" title="LSP TAG TLV">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |             Type  [TBD]       |             Length=8          |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |     Flags   |D|  Reserved     |          Tag                  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The LSP-TAG TLV is an optional TLV for use in the LSP Object
	  (<xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce"/>). Its format is shown in the 
	  above figure.  The type of the TLV is to be defined by IANA. The flags field 
	  defines a single flag, the dis-association flag.

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>D = 1:Dis-associate the tag specified in the TLV from the LSP specified in the LSP object. </t>
      </list>
      </t>

	  <t> On PCUpd, the D flag MAY be set by the PCE to request a dis-association of a tag it previously
	  set. XXX TBD - the error condition needs to be specified for the case where the disassociation 
	  is invalid. In a PCRpt message, the PCC MUST report all
	  the tags associated with an LSP. If a TAG is missing it is considered removed (this is to support
      reporting associations communicated via different mechanisms, for example configuration, as well
      as associations established by the PCE). </t> 
	  
	  <t> XXX TBD - add text on non-support. Can either do capability negotiation or just ignore the 
	  unknown TLV.</t> 
    </section> <!-- LSP-TAG-tlv --> 

 
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>IANA is requested to allocate a new TLV type (recommended value is
      TBD)for LSP-TAG TLV specified in this document.</t>

      <t>This document requests that a registry is created to manage the value
      of the Flag Type field in the LSP-TAG TLV. XXX TBD the flag values</t>

      <t>
	  XXX TBD - document errors 
      </t>
      
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"?>
	   <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5575.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-pce"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.crabbe-pce-pce-initiated-lsp"?>
    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
